《Wolfram笔记本简介》
中的本章节是
一个有关交互性功能
例如托盘和对话框的调查 // unconfirmed
这些功能在完成的应用 // unconfirmed
程序中很常见
Wolfram 笔记本系统有很多
这些功能的例子
例如
这是一个超链接对话框
它出现于上一个章节
就像大多数对话框
它就是一些交互式控件的集合
例如单选框和文本框
以及取消和完成超链接的按钮
交互性控件能被展示在
一个叫做“palette”的窗口中
例如
在“插入” (Insert) 菜单下
点击“特殊字符” (Special Characters)
会出现一个输入特殊字符的 palette
This palette shows
several grids of buttons,
with tabs for choosing
which grid to display.
Clicking any of the buttons
pastes that character
into the notebook.
For complete
standalone applications,
quite a lot can be done
using the Manipulate function.
For example,
here is a Manipulate result
from the Wolfram Demonstrations
Project website.
This application gives controls
for plotting countries
of the world
based on properties selected
from two popup menus.
There are also buttons
for choosing linear
or logarithmic scales
for the plot
and for choosing
whether each country
should be shown as a dot
or as the flag of the country
or as the name of the country.
The purpose of this section
is to describe a few details
of how these interactive
interfaces are constructed.
Starting with Manipulate,
here is a simpler example
with two sliders
for controlling the position
of a point in an image.
A potentially more intuitive
arrangement of these controls
would be to make the control
for the vertical coordinate
into a vertical slider
and position it
on the left side of the image,
which can be done
using the ControlType
and ControlPlacement options.
The control could also be
a two-dimensional slider,
which can be specified
using Slider2D.
There is also a control
called a Locator
that puts the control
right on the image.
Returning for now though
to the two-dimensional slider,
it is easy to imagine extending
this example with more controls.
For example, this input gives
four two-dimensional sliders
for controlling opposite ends
of two line segments.
In examples like this
with many controls,
it can be useful
to organize the controls
in some meaningful layout,
which can be done
using the same layout functions
that are used elsewhere
in a notebook.
One layout function
that is useful
in this example is Grid,
which displays expressions
in a two-dimensional grid.
The elements in that grid
can be anything, including,
for example, controls like
two-dimensional sliders.
To use the Grid function
in Manipulate, add curly braces
so that the control specifications
become elements of an array
and enclose that array in Grid.
One remaining detail
to complete this input
is enclosing
each slider specification
in the Control function.
The Control function
has previously been unnecessary,
but it is needed here
to distinguish the lists
that specify the controls
from the lists
that are part of the array,
and also to distinguish controls
from other layout functions.
The result is a display with
the sliders arranged in a grid.
Functions like TabView
can also be used in Manipulate.
For example,
this uses the TabView function
to put each control
on a different tab.
There are many
other ways of labeling
and arranging controls.
For example, returning
to the earlier example,
most of the programming here
is in the first argument
of the Manipulate function.
The controls are specified
in a few lines at the end.
There is a label,
followed by a specification
that gives a popup menu
for choosing the vertical
variable in the plot.
The next specification
gives a control
called a setter bar
for choosing whether to use
a logarithmic scale
or a linear scale
on the vertical axis.
Delimiter draws the lines
between groups of controls.
After that are similar controls
for the horizontal axis,
and at the end
is a row of buttons
for choosing whether to plot
each country as a point
or as a flag
or as the name of a country.
The control types
are determined automatically
based on how
the variable is specified.
You can use
the ControlType option
to specify a different control.
For example, this specifies
that the first scale control
should be a RadioButtonBar,
rather than a SetterBar.
The behavior of the program
with the radio buttons
is the same as before,
but the control
for that one variable
has a different appearance.
There are many other things
that can be done with Manipulate.
A good source of examples
is the Wolfram Demonstrations
Project website,
where you can find thousands
of examples submitted by users,
and there are also good tutorials
on the Manipulate function
in the Wolfram documentation.
Manipulate is useful
for standalone applications,
where the controls and display
are all in the same place,
but there are many applications
where it is useful to put
the controls somewhere else.
One place to put controls
is in a separate window,
called a palette.
Here is the example
shown earlier, which is
the special characters palette.
This palette is a collection
of buttons called paste buttons,
which can be generated using
a function called PasteButton.
For example, this gives
a paste button
that pastes the letters ABC
into the current notebook.
You can create a grid of buttons,
like the grids in
the special characters palette
using the Grid function.
That grid can then
be converted into a palette,
using the CreatePalette function.
The buttons in that palette
can then be used
to insert characters
into the notebook.
This palette could also have
been generated by selecting
the grid of buttons and choosing
Create Palette from Selection
under the Palettes menu.
Palettes can also include controls
other than paste buttons.
For example,
this input gives a palette
with a popup menu
for choosing a location
and a paste button
for pasting the chosen location
into a notebook.
One common use of palettes is
for entering function templates.
For example, consider a project
where there is some
frequently used input,
like this input that gives
the current temperature
and the local time
for a location.
Rather than entering that entire
input for each new location,
we could instead start
with a template like this,
with a small black square
called a selection placeholder
in place of the location.
The small black square
is a special character
that can be entered
in several different ways,
one of which is to
type a backslash
and an open square bracket
and then the name
of the character.
The name of this character
is SelectionPlaceholder.
The SelectionPlaceholder
character appears as soon as
the closing square bracket
is entered.
A palette with a button
to enter that template
can be generated
by first creating the button.
In this input,
the Defer function is included
so that the program
does not get evaluated
until after a value
is inserted for the placeholder.
The Defer function, or something
that has the same effect,
is a common requirement
in examples like this one.
The result is a button
that can be used
just by clicking the button
and inserting a value
for the placeholder,
or we could instead start
by entering a location,
selecting the location,
clicking the button
to generate the input,
which automatically inserts
the selection into the template,
and then evaluating
the resulting input.
A shorter label for that button
can be entered
by including the label
as the first argument
in the PasteButton function.
Then move the button to a palette
using the CreatePalette function,
which gives a palette
with one button.
The button in the palette
works just like the button
that was created earlier.
Another interactive way
to generate that same result
is with a dialog box.
For example, here is an input
that uses the DialogInput function
to generate a dialog box
with the popup menu
for selecting a location,
and clicking Done
evaluates the program
that generates the time
and temperature result.
To break that input
down a little bit,
this input uses
the DialogueInput function
to give a dialog box
with just two buttons,
which are created
by the ChoiceButtons function.
Clicking the Cancel button
returns $Canceled,
and clicking OK
just closes the dialog box.
The dialog box can be made
to return something
by including
the DialogueReturn function
in the arguments
of the ChoiceButtons function.
For example, this input
gives a dialog box
where clicking Done
returns a number
and clicking Cancel
returns the symbol $Canceled.
To get the dialog box
for time and temperature data,
we can modify this program
to run the time
and temperature program
rather than just
returning a number,
and include a popup menu
for selecting the location.
Two other modifications
in this program
are the addition
of DynamicModule
and the Column function.
The Column function is included
so that the popup menu
and the choice buttons
are displayed in a column
and DynamicModule is included
to localize the variable loc,
since the popup menu
would otherwise assign
a global value to that variable,
which could be a problem
if a variable with the same name
is used somewhere else
in the project.
Before closing this section,
one other place
to put interactive controls
is in a fixed location
at the top of the notebook
using a feature
called a docked cell.
A docked cell can be created
by setting the DockedCells option
of the current notebook.
For example, this input
introduces a docked cell
with some text.
Usually the input
for a docked cell
is a raw cell expression
and not just some text,
and the recommended cell style
for that cell
is DockedCell,
as in this input.
Docked cells are typically used
for controls or for anything else
that is used throughout
a notebook.
For example, here is a notebook
with a popup menu
for selecting a location
and several elements
within that notebook
that depend on that selection.
The TrackedSymbols option
is included here
so that those elements
are only updated
when the location is changed,
instead of updating whenever
there are changes in things
like the time or the temperature.
This is an example
where it could be useful
to put the popup menu
in a docked cell.
Start by setting the cell style
to DockedCell
using the Style submenu
under the Format menu,
and then copy the cell
by choosing
Copy As ▶ Cell Expression
from the Edit menu.
Then paste that cell
into the input
that sets the value
of the DockedCells option
for this notebook.
This brings up a dialog box
asking if the cells
should be interpreted
or should be pasted
as a cell expression.
In this example,
the intention is to use
the raw uninterpreted
cell expression,
so select No and then evaluate
the resulting input
to put the popup menu
in a docked cell
at the top of the notebook.
That's the end of the examples
for this section.
There is much more to be said
about all of the topics
that came up in this brief tour
of features for constructing
interactive program interfaces.
A good place to start
to find more information
in the Wolfram Documentation
is this page on
Custom Interface Construction,
which includes links
to documentation
for all of the topics
that came up in this section.