这一章节的《Wolfram 笔记本介绍》
讲解了一个更合适的表格格式化工具
就像这里所示的表格
and is specifically about options for setting up details,
例如分割线
还有交错底色的横行
还有调整表格中每个单元格外观的工具
让我们从第一个样例开始
这里是生成一个表格范例的输入
执行这个输入，我们得到了一个输出单元
我将把它转换为文本单元
因为大多数单元格内都是纯文本
这个输入使用了 Grid 内置符号
Grid 内置符号的第一个参数
是真正被放在表格中的数组
该数组给出了表头和占位符
这里有六个选项
“背景”(Background) 选项设置表格的背景为
横行交错使用白色和灰色
如果我点击表格内部
然后按下 Ctrl + 回车 以增加更多的行
交错的背景颜色会在新行中继续延伸
“排列” (Alignment) 选项指定了
每一列中文本的水平对齐方式
和每一行中文本的垂直对齐方式
“分割线” (Dividers) 选项用来绘制行与行之间的分割线
这就是定义表头之下绘制粗分割线的地方
below the heading is specified.
“基本样式” (BaseStyle) 选项
定义了表格中文字所用的字体
最后，对象大小 (ItemSize) 选项
specifies the space to allow for each column,
“间隔” (Spacings) 选项定义了列于列之间的空隙大小
即使被这些选项控制的细节非常多
它的基本思想依然很简单
可以发现，许多选项都有着相似的设计
只需观察他们的效果即可阐明表格中的这些设计
（译注：需要一定的英语基础）
on a generic table.
这里有一个带有占位符文本的表格
它的“边框” (Frame) 选项被设置为“全部” (All)
以帮助我们清楚的观察行和列
从“背景” (Background) 选项开始
它可以设置成单色
要设置整个网格的背景颜色
but the general form of the Background option
is a list with three elements
where the first element
specifies the background for columns,
the second element specifies the background for rows
and the third element can be used to specify
the background for individual elements in the table.
For example, entering Red, Green, Blue
in the first element
causes the first three columns to be red, green and blue.
Enclosing colors in a list
causes those colors to be repeated across the table.
For example, this gives red for the first column
and repeated green and blue columns
for the rest of the table.
The same structure applies to rows.
For example,
if that same color specification is the second element
in the value of the Background option,
the result is a table where the first row is red
and the remaining rows alternate between green and blue.
The third element in the value of the Background option
can be used for specifying the background color
of individual entries in the table.
For example, this specifies
that the seventh element in the fourth row
should have an orange background.
Similar principles apply to the Dividers option
and to the Alignment option and to all of the options
that control specific rows and columns.
For example, this shows a value for the Dividers option
that gives a column divider every third column
and a row divider above the second row.
As with the Background option,
the value of the Dividers option is a list.
The first element of that list specifies column dividers
and the second element specifies row dividers.
The dividers can also have styles.
For example, this specifies that the column dividers
should be repeated thick lines and light gray lines,
and that the horizontal divider below the top row
should be a thick red line.
With those general principles in mind,
here again is the first example,
where I will go ahead and fill in some values in the table.
This value of the Background option
gives the alternating
white and light gray background for the rows.
The Alignment option specifies
that items in the first column should be centered horizontally.
The second column should be aligned on the right,
as is typically done for columns of numbers
and items in the third column are aligned on the left.
This value of the Dividers option
gives the thick line below the top row
and the light gray dividers for all of the rows after that.
The light gray divider becomes part of the background
for all of the rows except the last one,
where the divider shows up
as a light grey line at the bottom of the table.
The BaseStyle option specifies the default font
to use for all of the items in the table.
The ItemSize option here
specifies the width of each column.
The first two columns are given as scaled amounts,
which means that they are scaled to a fraction
of the formatting width,
which is related to the width of the window.
So the width of the columns changes
with the width of the display,
which can be desirable
if the table might be displayed in different windows.
Finally, this value of the Spacings option
adds some space between the last two columns.
A good way to learn what these options do
is to try different values for the options
and observe the effect on the table.
For example, here is a simple Manipulate program
that gives a control
for adjusting the space between the last two columns.
Rather than using options for the Grid function,
a separate strategy for specifying styles
is to use Item expressions as elements in the table
and to specify options within each Item expression.
For example, rather than using the Background option
to specify the background color
of a particular entry in the table,
another way to get the same effect
is to make that one element into an Item expression
and to include the Background option
in that Item expression.
A related feature is using the special symbols
SpanFromLeft, SpanFromAbove and SpanFromBoth
to get table entries that span more than one row
or more than one column.
For example, here is a small table of placeholders.
Replacing one of those placeholders
with the special symbol SpanFromLeft
causes that entry in the table
to be merged with the entry to the left.
There are also symbols called SpanFromAbove
and SpanFromBoth
that can be used to merge entries vertically or in both directions.
The affect actually ends up being the same
as selecting items to be merged
and choosing Make Spanning from the Table/Matrix submenu.
As a final example which uses several of these tools,
here is the second of the two tables
that were shown earlier
together with an input to generate that table.
This input again
uses the Grid function with several options.
The ItemSize option specifies columns
with a width of three,
which means three units called ems.
An em is a unit
equal to the point size of the current font.
If the ItemSize option is omitted,
then the columns are adjusted to the width of the widest item
in the column,
which here gives a table with columns
that seem a bit too narrow,
so the ItemSize option is included
to give a table that is not quite so cramped.
This value of the Frame option draws the divider lines
and the frame around the table.
This value of the Alignment option specifies that
items should be centered both vertically and horizontally
and the Background option
specifies a light gray background for the top row
and alternating orange
and light blue background, for the remaining rows.
Background is used in this table
as a color code for the T and F entries in the table.
The Background option happens in this example
to give the correct color for all of the entries,
except for one
where the background is specified in an Item expression.
Without that Item expression,
the color for that item would be light blue,
which doesn't follow the intended color code.
This table also includes two SpanFromAbove entries,
which are there to generate the two items in the first column
that span more than one row.
That's the end of the examples for this section.
A good source for additional information
is the documentation for the Grid function
and related functions,
and especially this tutorial on grids, rows and columns.
And it is of course almost always useful
to just construct a generic table
and try these things out for yourself.