这一章节的《 Wolfram 笔记本介绍》的内容
是使用笔记本进行演示
例如以幻灯片的形式显示笔记本
这里是一个典型的幻灯片的例子
它本质上只是一个笔记本
并且每次显示一张幻灯片
你可以通过点击显示屏右上角的这个按钮
(-)
待对照！！！然后在弹出的菜单中选择" "来结束幻灯片放映
这样会在工作格式下显示同一个笔记本
这个笔记本用来创建幻灯片
This working slideshow notebook
和其他的笔记本几乎一样
不过有两个基本的区别
一是两张幻灯片直接有空隙分隔
二是是笔记本顶部会显示创作工具栏
！！不通顺：创作工具栏是一个停靠在顶端的单元
The authoring toolbar is a docked cell
带有常见操作的控件
例如插入新幻灯片页面、开始演示
The authoring toolbar and the Slide Break cells
and all of the other options that make this notebook
function as an environment for creating a slideshow
are set up in the stylesheet.
The stylesheet for this notebook
is chosen from the PresenterTools submenu
under the Format ► Stylesheet menu.
All of the stylesheets in the PresenterTools submenu
include all of the options for creating a slideshow.
In fact, any notebook can be made into a slideshow
by simply choosing one of the PresenterTools stylesheets
and inserting slide breaks.
For example, here is that same notebook,
but without any of the Slide Break cells
and with the normal Default stylesheet,
which is the item that is checked in the stylesheet submenu.
Further down this menu is the PresenterTools submenu,
and below that is another submenu called SlideShow.
The SlideShow submenu is included
to support an older slideshow system
that has been available
in Wolfram Notebooks for many years.
But this section is about the newer PresenterTools system,
which is an enhanced version of the older system.
To make this notebook into a slideshow,
we will choose one of the PresenterTools stylesheets.
A convenient way to insert slide breaks
is to first bring up the authoring toolbar,
which is made visible by changing
the screen environment to Slideshow Working,
using the Screen Environment submenu under the Format menu.
Clicking the Insert New Slide button
in the authoring toolbar opens a short popup menu
offering to insert a slide break with or without a background.
Either choice inserts the slide break,
which is marked by a new cell
with a cell style called slideshow navigation bar.
You can also create a new slide
by copying and pasting the Slide Break cell
from elsewhere in the notebook.
For example, we can select the Slide Break cell
and the Section cell below it,
and then copy that selection and paste those cells elsewhere
in the notebook to get a new slide.
This sort of editing is also a way of deleting slides
or deleting slide breaks.
For example, to delete the slide that was just added,
we can select the Slide Break cell
and the contents of the slide and delete that selection.
Another way of inserting slide breaks
throughout the notebook
is to click the Slide Break Defaults button
in the authoring toolbar,
which opens a dialog box
where you can choose slide breaks based on cell styles.
For example, choosing Section in this dialog box
and clicking the Set button inserts a slide break
before every Section cell in the notebook.
If the notebook is already organized into sections,
this is a fast way of turning the notebook into a slideshow.
Rather than converting a default notebook
into a slideshow,
in many cases
the easiest way to create a new slideshow
is to start by choosing New ► Presenter Notebook
from the File menu,
which brings up this dialog box
for choosing from the same set of PresenterTools stylesheets,
which are here referred to as themes.
From this dialog box you can also choose
from various default fonts and color schemes.
After making some choices,
click the Create button to get a slideshow template
with the chosen PresenterTools stylesheet
and the screen environment set to Slideshow Working
and the authoring toolbar at the top and several slides
with some generic content already filled in.
This notebook can then be edited much like any other notebook
to fill in the contents of the slideshow.
Several of the buttons in the authoring toolbar
are generic controls for fonts and styling
that could apply to any notebook.
For example, this button brings up a menu
for choosing cell style,
which are the same styles that can be chosen
from the Style submenu under the Format menu.
Next to the cell style menu
is an interesting button that can be used
to add font choices to all cells of the selected style.
For example,
after setting this text cell to use large, bold characters,
clicking that button has the effect
of applying those options to all of the text cells
in the notebook.
This worked by editing the private stylesheet
for this notebook.
For example,
choosing Edit Stylesheet from the Format menu
shows the private stylesheet for this notebook
with the new local style definitions
that specify large, bold characters for the text.
You could achieve the same effect
by editing the stylesheet directly,
so that button in the authoring toolbar
essentially provides
one-click editing of the stylesheet.
One button that is worth saying a few words about
is this button, which opens a popup menu
for making font sizes larger or smaller.
To describe what that menu does, it is helpful to first bring up
a feature of all PresenterTools stylesheets,
which is dynamic resizing of content
depending on the size of the window.
For example, if the size of this window is changed,
the font sizes change, and in fact the sizes of images
and almost all of the other content
within the notebook also changes based on the size of the window.
You could get the same effect in any notebook
by using scaled sizes for fonts and images and so on,
but unlike most other stylesheets, with PresenterTools stylesheets
all of the options settings for that resizing
are already part of the stylesheet.
Dynamic resizing like this
is helpful for the common situation
where you want to enlarge the window for presentation
or where the presentation is done on a different display system
where window sizes might be different.
Returning now to the specific issue of font sizes,
if font size is specified by selecting some text
and choosing a font size from the Size submenu
under the Format menu,
the size of that text remains constant
as the size of the window is changed,
since that size setting takes precedence
over the dynamic resizing system from the stylesheet.
The font size button
in the authoring toolbar works differently.
For example, selecting some text and then choosing a new size
from the popup menu in the authoring toolbar
causes the size of the selected text
to be scaled up or down by the chosen number of steps,
and the resized text does change size
based on the size of the window.
Similar issues also apply to images and to graphics.
For example, selecting this image
changes the authoring toolbar
to show a button for locking the current size of the image
or letting the size of the image change
with the size of the window.
Choosing Lock to current size
sets the image size option for that selection
to the current fixed value,
which results in an image that, like the text shown earlier,
remains at a fixed size
when the size of the window is changed.
So while dynamic resizing is the default,
you can get fixed sizes by specifying sizes
for individual selections.
Other buttons in the authoring toolbar
include the Start Presentation button,
which is the button to click to start the presentation,
which we will do in a moment.
The first button below the Start Presentation button
brings up a palette of buttons
showing the outline of the slideshow.
These buttons can be clicked
to navigate between slides in the notebook.
This palette also includes a refresh button
to update the palette if slides are added or removed.
The button next to that opens the Side Notes palette,
which provides a way of adding notes
that are intended for the presenter
and that will be shown in this palette,
but that are not displayed in the presentation.
To add a side note,
click the Add note to slide button,
which inserts a cell called a SideNote cell
into the slideshow notebook.
This cell can be edited just like any other cell.
Clicking the refresh button updates the Side Notes palette
with any new side notes.
Clicking this last button opens a popup menu.
Choosing Style Palette from that menu
opens a palette of buttons
like the buttons in the authoring toolbar.
Choosing Presentation Controls
opens a dialog box for customizing the computer keys
for navigating between slides.
Choosing Theme Options opens the same dialog box
that was used initially for choosing a stylesheet.
So if you wanted to change the stylesheet
from the stylesheet that was chosen initially,
you can do that here,
or equivalently, by choosing a different stylesheet
from the Stylesheet submenu.
For example, this changes the fonts
and the color scheme of the presentation
by changing the stylesheet.
To start the slideshow,
we can click the Start Presentation button.
At the end of the Start Presentation button
is a popup menu for other screen environments.
Scrolling Presentation gives a display
for scrolling through the slides
rather than clicking from slide to slide,
and Slideshow Presentation
switches the screen environment to Slideshow Presentation,
which removes the authoring toolbar
and the Slide Break cells and the SideNote cells.
Clicking the main Start Presentation button
does all of that
and also switches to full-screen display.
After the presentation is started,
you can move between slides
using keys on the computer keyboard
or the corresponding keys on a separate controller.
Within the slideshow, there is a button
in the upper-right corner of the window
that can be clicked
to open a popup menu with other controls.
There are choices here for moving to the first slide
or to the next slide and so on.
Choosing Toggle Navigation Bar adds on-screen controls
at the top of the window for moving between slides.
Choosing Toggle Style Tools opens the same palette
of style controls that was shown earlier.
In Slideshow Working screen environment,
this palette isn't usually needed since the same controls
are available in the authoring toolbar,
but here this palette provides a way of editing the slideshow
from within the actual presentation,
rather than from the working notebook environment.
Choosing Side Notes
opens the Side Notes palette to show side notes,
which you could display on a different monitor
or on a separate tablet or other device.
You can also click within this palette
to move between slides.
Choosing Slide Outline opens the Slide Outline palette
that was shown earlier,
which provides yet another way of moving between slides.
Going beyond a basic slideshow like this,
there's an unlimited range of possibilities
for what is displayed in a presentation
and for how that display is controlled.
To illustrate some of the possibilities,
consider this animation,
which is used for illustrating a topic
that comes up during this particular presentation.
During a presentation,
the presenter can control this animation
using the controls in the display.
There are, however, situations where it would be better
to have the controls somewhere else,
such as in a separate controller.
There are several ways to do that,
one of which is shown here.
This example shows a display in the presentation
that depends on a dynamically updated variable
and a button in a separate notebook
for controlling the value of that variable.
This allows the presentation
to be controlled by a separate controller,
which is useful in settings
where it is inconvenient for the presenter
to click on buttons in the display.
Wolfram Notebooks support a whole collection of features
for programmatic control of the display,
so it is possible to design presentations
with complex animations or sequences of images,
and to program all of that in advance
so that it can be shown during the presentation
with the click of a button on an off-screen controller.
That's the end of the examples for this section.
In the Wolfram documentation, you can find more information
by searching for presentations or slideshows,
and in particular from this page
on preparing and giving presentations,
which includes links to workflow guides like this one,
with step-by-step instructions
for the operations that came up in this section.