这一章节的《Wolfram 笔记本介绍》
是关于使用程序和模板
来自动产生笔记本和文档
自动产生文档在实际应用中很有用
比如处理那些以某种方式重复的文档
就像这里展示出的一系列报告
或者是处理有相同内容的文档
像是这个笔记本
或者是应用于一些更加专业的场景
像是处理按日程编写的报告
处理计算合同
或者只是记录长时间运行的程序结果
待会将要详细介绍的
一个处理报告的基本过程
会从创建一个像这样的简单模板笔记本开始
然后用那个模板填充信息
去产生一个文件
这个输入用了 GenerateDocument 函数
和被保存在文件中的
模板里的名称参数
另一个产生文件的更低级的方式
是写一个这样的程序
含有 CreateDocument 和 NotebookWrite 函数
去产生一个笔记本文件
然后在这个笔记本中插入内容
产生笔记本的任何方式
基本上都是可能的
因为 Wolfram 笔记本
是由 Wolfram 语言表达的
而且可以被 Wolfram 语言程序
创建和修改
将一个笔记本描述为一系列单元(Cell)
字面上是说这个笔记本的内容
是一个 Wolfram 语言中的列表(List)
拥有很多个单元(Cell)表达式作为元素
比如 这里是一个笔记本的表达式
拥有三个单元(Cell)
和指定笔记本窗口顶端标题、窗口大小
的选项
使用 NotebookPut 函数
这个表达式可以作为一个笔记本被展示
直接输入笔记本表达式
不是笔记本被创建的方式
但是笔记本最终完成于
笔记本表达式的操作
其中一个操作就是 CreateNotebook 函数
用在这里去创建一个新的笔记本表达式
然后在计算机屏幕上展示
这个输入同时分配了笔记本对象
和变量的值
将内容输入进笔记本的一个方式
是用 NotebookWrite 函数
将单元(Cell)表达式插入笔记本
All of the general programming
features of the Wolfram Language
can also be used
in generating notebooks.
For example,
starting with some data
to form the basis for a report,
here is a program
that creates a new notebook,
writes a title cell
into that notebook
and then uses
NotebookWrite commands in a loop
to generate a notebook
with a section for each element
in the data list.
Beyond CreateNotebook
and NotebookWrite,
there are many other functions
for manipulating notebooks.
You can find more information
about those functions
in the Wolfram documentation,
such as in this page
on manipulating notebooks
from the kernel.
There are functions here
for moving around
and searching within a notebook,
for inserting
and deleting content,
for opening and closing
notebooks, and so on.
Basically almost anything
that can be done
by interactively editing
this notebook
can also be done from a program.
A more graphical way
of generating notebooks
is the method mentioned earlier
of starting with
a template notebook like this one
and inserting content
within that template.
A template notebook
can be created by choosing New ►
Programmatic Notebook ►
Template Notebook
from the File menu,
which opens a new notebook
with a toolbar in a docked cell
at the top of the notebook.
Except for the toolbar,
this notebook can be edited
much like any other notebook.
The report is completed
either by inserting expressions
at locations called slots
within this notebook
or by doing evaluations
within the template
when the report is generated.
You can add a slot
by clicking the Slot button,
which opens a dialog box
for entering the name of the slot,
and you can optionally enter
default values for each slot.
After finishing the template,
you can click the Generate button
to generate a report
with the slots filled in
by the default values,
which is useful for checking
that the template
is giving the expected result.
The template notebook
can also be saved for later use
like any other notebook
by choosing Save
under the File menu.
After creating the template,
there are several tools
for filling in the slots
in the template.
One of those tools
is the GenerateDocument function,
shown here with the name
of the saved template notebook
as the first argument
and a list of rules giving values
for the named template slots
as the second argument.
The result is a report
with the template slots
filled in with
the specified values.
Rather than
evaluating expressions
and inserting the results
into slots in the template,
it is also possible,
and often makes
the document-generation process
somewhat easier,
to do those evaluations
right within the template.
For example,
the DateString expression
in that GenerateDocument input,
which is evaluated
to get a result
that is inserted into a slot
in the template,
could alternatively be included
right in the template
using the Expression button
in the template toolbar.
Clicking the Expression button
gives a box
where you can enter
an expression to be evaluated
when the document generated.
After saving
the revised template,
we can return
to the GenerateDocument input,
where the DateString expression
is no longer needed.
When the document is generated,
the output from evaluating
the DateString expression
in the template is inserted
and the document looks
just as it did before,
but that GenerateDocument input
is a bit less complicated.
Reports can be much more
elaborate than this one
and can include tables
and graphs and anything else
that can be included
in any notebook.
For example, here is a plot
using data from a dataset
that is loaded
from an external file.
This plot can be added
to the report
by including another slot
in the template, as shown here;
saving the revised template;
then moving over
to the GenerateDocument input
to enter a value
for the new named slot
and evaluating that input
to generate the report.
As was used earlier
for the DateString expression,
the programming to load the data
and generate the plot
in that example
can also be put in the template.
A direct way of doing that
is to simply edit the template
to add the inputs
to load the data
and generate the plot.
If we click the Generate button
for this template,
the inputs and outputs
are all included in the report.
If the report
only needs to show the plot,
the inputs can be omitted
with the help of items
under the Cell Behavior menu
in the report template toolbar.
To evaluate
and then delete the cell
with the input
for loading the data,
select that cell
and choose Evaluate and Delete
from the Cell Behavior menu.
For the cell with the input
that generates the plot,
we could again choose
Evaluate and Delete,
which would show the plot
and delete the input,
or we can choose
Evaluate and Hide.
Clicking the Generate button
shows the effect
of those settings.
The cell for loading the data,
which was set to
Evaluate and Delete,
was evaluated and deleted,
and the cell
for generating the plot,
which was set to
Evaluate and Hide,
gives the plot shown
in a closed cell group.
Double-clicking on the closed
cell group bracket
opens that cell group
to show the input,
which can be useful
if users of the report
might want to see that input.
Other choices
for cell behavior are
Leave Unevaluated,
which copies the chosen cell
over to the report
without doing any evaluation,
and Exclude Cell,
which omits the cell
from the report,
also without evaluating it,
which is useful
for saving notes and comments
that are not part of the report.
The programming in that example
brings up a technical detail
that can sometimes be important
to know about,
which is that the notebooks
for the report template
and for the generated report
have an option setting
that causes new variables
to be assigned a context
that is unique to each notebook.
The new variable in question
in this example
is the data variable.
By default, the context
of new variables
is global in all notebooks,
so a new variable
in one notebook
is the same as a variable
with that same name
in another notebook.
In this generated notebook,
however,
the context is unique
to this notebook,
so values assigned
to this variable
in this notebook
have no effect on variables
with the same name
in another notebook.
Normally this is
desirable behavior,
but if report generation
is for some reason set up
to depend on
global names for variables,
then it is necessary
to specify the context explicitly
or to otherwise arrange
for those variables
to use the same context.
The most common reason
for creating a template
is for creating
more than one report,
which in part means
being careful to program
into the template
only the content and formatting
that is common
to all of the reports.
As an example, consider
generating a separate report
for each record in the dataset
that was loaded earlier.
That dataset consists
of a list of records
and the example template
is programmed to show
only the first record.
This data happens
to be in the form
of a Wolfram Language dataset,
from which it is easy
to extract an expression
called an association
for the elements in each record.
This association can be used
in the GenerateDocument function,
just like the list of rules
that was used earlier
for named slots in a template.
To make the template work
with this dataset,
we can modify the template
so that the names of the named
slots in the template
match the names
of the named items
in each record in the dataset.
After saving the revised template,
the GenerateDocument function
can be used with the association
extracted from the dataset
to generate a report.
Applying the Normal function
to the entire dataset
gives a list of associations
for each record,
and each association
has the names and values to use
in the GenerateDocument function
to generate the document.
All that remains now
is to write a short program
to apply
the GenerateDocument function
to each element in that list,
which results in a separate
report being generated
for each record in the dataset.
Rather than creating
separate reports,
a report based on this dataset
could alternatively
be a single document
with a separate section
for each record in the dataset.
One way of generating
such a report
uses the Repeating Block feature
in the template toolbar.
To demonstrate
how repeating block works
in a simple example,
here is a template
with two cells.
To repeat these two cells,
select the cell bracket
and click
the Repeating Block button,
which opens a dialog box
with several choices.
Here we will demonstrate
only the second choice,
which specifies
that this template
will use a variable named data
and that the value
of that variable
will be a list for filling in
the slots in each block.
A GenerateDocument input to use
this template can look like this,
where the value
of the data variable
is a list of associations
and each association
gives a list of named values
for filling in the slots
in each block.
In this example,
the value of the data variable
has three elements,
so the block will be repeated
three times in the report.
Returning to
the previous dataset,
rather than applying
GenerateDocument separately
to each record in the dataset,
this time the entire list
of associations
from that dataset
will be passed
to the GenerateDocument function
as the value of the variable
named data.
Now modify the earlier template
to use a repeating block
with named slots
that match the names
of the elements in each record.
After that modification,
the GenerateDocument program
to create the report
is just a single line of input.
All of the formatting
and interactive features
of notebooks that have come up
in earlier sections
can also be used in
automatically generated reports.
For example,
here is a template
that uses the Grid function
to show data in a table
and a TabView input
so that users of the report
can choose between different plots.
The report generated
from that template
is an interactive report
with a summary table
and an interactive feature
for selecting different
information to display.
That's the end of the examples
for this section.
There are many variations
on the basic
report-generation process.
In the Wolfram documentation,
you can find more information
by searching
for report generation.
For example, this guide page
gives links to the functions
that came up in the section
and also functions for doing
document generation in the cloud
and for such things
as generating reports
automatically on a schedule.
There are also workflow guides
with step-by-step instructions
for the basic process
of generating a report
from a template
and for generating a report
on schedule or as a PDF file.