这一章节的《Wolfram 笔记本介绍》
是关于在不同的平台上使用笔记本的
特别是在 Cloud 和在移动设备上
像是平板电脑和智能手机
比如说 这里是一个平板电脑上的笔记本
通过免费的 Wolfram Player 应用展示
在这个应用中你可以滚动笔记本
双击单元组括号
来打开和关闭单元
像 Wolfram 桌面端一样
而且这个笔记本也可变成动态的文件
所以比如说 你可以调整动态内容
像是这里的按钮和滑动条
Wolfram Player 应用中 交互式的操控内容
在屏幕底部展示
因为移动设备的控制
主要由手指触摸实现
而不是鼠标 并且手指可以阻挡展示的内容
所以在屏幕底部有控制栏
可以同时让观看展示
和进行控制更加简单
你可以使用 Wolfram Cloud 应用而不是 Wolfram Player
来创建或者编辑一个笔记本
比如说 这里展示了同一个笔记本
在 Wolfram Cloud 应用中的样子
包括编辑笔记本的控制选项
这些控制选项在这里使用来插入一个新的文本单元
编辑的具体操作会在稍后被说明
Wolfram Player 和 Wolfram Cloud 应用
在智能手机上也可以被使用
比如说 这是那个笔记本在手机上被展示
使用 Wolfram Player 应用
除了屏幕的大小不同
它与在平板电脑上没有什么区别
包括按钮和滑动条这些动态内容
笔记本也可以在网页浏览器中被展示和编辑
使用连接到互联网
或者合适的 Cloud 上的任何电脑
比如说 这里展示了电脑浏览器中
一个网页上的笔记本
它被登录到了免费 Wolfram Cloud 账户中
互动性的操作在这里也可以被实现
笔记本在这也可以被编辑
例如添加一个新的文本单元和做计算
当然 笔记本可以在
普通的电脑应用中被展示
比如说 这里展示了
Wolfram 桌面端中的笔记本
笔记本文件的基础
在所有平台中都相同
在手机端 在网页浏览器中
或者在桌面端
相同的笔记本可以在任何平台下被打开
比如说 从桌面端的这个笔记本开始 你可以选择
保存到 Wolfram Cloud (Save to Cloud)
来在 Cloud 账号中保存
如果桌面端应用没有登入
Wolfram Cloud 账号 你会被要求登入
之后你可以选择一个名称
来在那个账号中保存笔记本
Cloud 中的笔记本
可以在任何平台中被打开
比如说 回到平板电脑
在安装 Wolfram Player 应用后
你可以启动这个应用 它将会展示
保存在这个设备里的笔记本
想要看到刚才
被上传到 Cloud 的那个笔记本
你可以点击屏幕左上角的按钮
打开侧边栏 点击 Add Cloud Account
然后使用这个对话框来登入 Cloud 账户
The notebook that was
just saved to the cloud
was saved in the home directory
of that account,
so navigate to that directory
and open the notebook.
There are buttons in the upper-
right corner of this window
for various operations
with this notebook.
Tapping the button
with letters on it
opens a small dialog box
that is used here to make
the display a little bit bigger,
which results in the display
that was shown earlier.
This notebook currently exists
in the cloud,
but you can also save
the notebook locally
on this tablet computer
by tapping this button
in the upper-right corner
of the window,
which opens a dialog box
with various choices.
To save the notebook
on this tablet,
tap Save to Files,
which opens a dialog box
for choosing where
to save the notebook.
With the notebook saved
on this tablet,
you could sign out
of the cloud account
and even disconnect
from the internet
and still view the notebook.
The basic programs for
interacting with this notebook
are all running locally
on this tablet,
which makes these operations
significantly faster,
since it avoids the overhead
of running over the internet,
and dynamic content like buttons
and sliders will also work.
Working without being connected
to the internet, of course,
requires that nothing
in these operations
either directly or indirectly
tries to access the internet.
In this particular notebook,
the earthquake data, for example,
has to be included
in the notebook.
To edit the notebook
still on the tablet,
you can start by launching
the Wolfram Cloud app.
After logging into the account,
you can tap to open the notebook.
The display includes
the same font magnification
button as the Wolfram Player app.
Editing the notebook
to insert a new cell
starts much as it does
on the desktop
by clicking, or in this case
tapping, to get
a cell insertion bar,
which also brings up
a row of buttons
at the bottom of the screen.
To enter a calculation,
tap the Input cell button,
which creates a new Input cell
and also brings up
a special keyboard
for entering input.
You can use the keyboard
to enter the input
and then tap the evaluate button
to do the calculation.
To get a Text cell,
tap the new cell button
and choose Plain Text,
which creates a Text cell
and opens a keyboard
for entering the contents
of the cell.
Other types of cells
can be entered
by choosing Styled Text
from the new cell menu.
For example,
you can choose Section
to get a Section cell
and then enter the contents
of the cell.
Selecting cell brackets
brings up a different row
of buttons
for copying or pasting
or cutting cells.
For example, this shows
using the Cut button
to delete the cells
that were just entered.
Finally as was shown earlier,
Wolfram Notebooks
can also be edited
using a web browser.
You can start
at the Wolfram Cloud website.
Log in to your
Wolfram Cloud Account
and navigate to the notebook
that you want to edit.
Here you can enter calculations
by clicking in the notebook
to get a cell insertion bar,
enter the calculation
using the keyboard
and press SHIFT+ENTER
to do the calculation.
Many features of Wolfram Desktop
are also available here,
including, for example,
the Suggestions Bar
below the output.
Keyboard shortcuts can be used
for choosing new cell styles.
For example, you can type
the keyboard shortcut
for a new Text cell
and enter the contents
of the cell.
Another way of choosing
the style of a new cell
is to click the Format button
at the top of the window,
which opens a side panel
with controls for choosing fonts
and cell styles and so on.
For example,
to get a Section cell,
you can choose Section
from the Cell Style menu
and enter the contents
of the cell.
For just getting started
with Wolfram Notebooks,
Wolfram Cloud is in some ways
the easiest place to begin,
because usually
there's nothing to install.
All you need is a web browser
on a computer
connected to the internet.
For example,
you can open a web browser
and go to the Wolfram webpage,
www.wolfram.com,
which shows the whole range
of products.
One of those products
is Wolfram Programming Lab,
which is a good place for
learning the Wolfram Language.
Choosing Wolfram Programming Lab
opens a notebook
with some sample
Wolfram Language programs,
but to just get a new notebook,
you can click
the Create New Notebook button
or choose New Notebook
from the File menu
to get a new notebook
in the Wolfram Cloud |
Open Access system,
where you can enter content
and do calculations
much as you might do
in any other Wolfram Notebook.
After creating the notebook,
you can save the notebook
in the cloud,
which would of course require
logging into a cloud account,
or you can choose Download
from the File menu
to download the notebook
to a desktop system.
That's the end of the examples
for this section.
The basic features
of Wolfram Notebooks
work much the same
across all of these platforms,
but for features
that are different
on different platforms,
a good place to look
for more information
is the workflow guides
in the Wolfram documentation,
which gives separate
step-by-step instructions
for each platform.
For example, here is a page
of workflow guides
on working in notebooks,
and in this page
on creating a Text cell,
you can choose instructions
for the desktop platform
or for Wolfram Cloud
or for mobile devices
like tablets and smartphones.