Welcome to this short introduction
to Wolfram Notebooks.
Wolfram Notebooks
were first released in 1988,
as the user interface
for Wolfram Language systems.
So, a typical
Wolfram Language session
might look something like this,
with inputs and outputs displayed
in a notebook window.
Wolfram Notebooks
have always been much more
than just a user interface though.
In addition to inputs and outputs,
the notebook can include
headings and comments,
as shown here,
as well as project information
and hyperlinks
and anything else that you
might want put in the document.
Here is a more finished notebook,
with notes and tables
and interactive features
like buttons and sliders,
all organized into sections
and subsections.
A Wolfram Notebook like this is
uniquely itself, a programmable
Wolfram Language expression.
It can be saved to the cloud
for viewing in a web browser
or formatted
as a slide presentation
or shared as a standalone
electronic document
or viewed on mobile devices.
And a Wolfram Notebook
can be created
and edited programmatically
from the Wolfram Language,
which enables a broad range
of applications,
like generating
rich reports automatically
or even saving notebooks
as expressions in a blockchain,
for a computational contracts.
To see a few details of how
all of these features come together,
consider a project that starts
with an empty notebook.
This first input imports
some data related to earthquakes,
and this next input
organizes that data into a dataset.
There are a variety of aids
to help with getting the syntax right
when entering these inputs.
This next input will give a plot
of the geographic locations
of earthquakes.
And as this input
is being entered,
unmatched brackets
and quote marks
are shown in a different color,
and different types of keywords
are shown in different colors.
And for longer programs,
there are other programming aids
like automatic line breaking
and so on.
This shows another one
of those programming aids
called command completion,
which displays a menu of choices,
given the first few letters
in the name of a function.
And after the function is chosen,
you can bring up a menu
of function templates
for the arguments
of the function.
This input gives a histogram
of earthquake magnitudes.
Before a project like this
gets very far along,
it can be useful to include notes
and background information
to describe, say,
an overview of the project,
or to give details about
what each calculation is doing.
Notes like that, can be inserted
by clicking anywhere
between the inputs and outputs,
and entering text, much as
you might do in any text editor.
You can indicate
that you are entering text
by choosing Text
from the Style submenu,
under the format menu
or by using the equivalent
keyboard shortcut.
Eventually the notebook
can become large enough
that it is useful
to add some organization.
There are several ways
of doing that.
Here I will start
by entering a title
and then a section heading,
at the start of each new topic.
Section headings
are added much like text,
by clicking where you want
to put a heading
and choosing Section from the
Style submenu of the format menu
or by using the equivalent
keyboard shortcut.
A key feature of notebooks is that
notebooks are structured documents,
where everything in the notebook
is organized into units called cells.
There are many different
types of cells.
Inputs are shown in input cells.
Outputs are shown
in output cells.
Text is shown in text cells.
Section headings are shown
in section cells and so on.
Cells are typically identified
by cell brackets,
near the right edge
of the notebook window.
Cells can also be nested.
So, for example,
there is a cell bracket
that groups each input
with the corresponding output.
And in this notebook,
for each section heading
there is an outer bracket
that automatically groups
the section heading
with all of the cells in that section.
Returning now to the top
of the notebook,
one useful feature
of grouped cells
is that cell groups
can be opened and closed.
For example,
double-clicking on
the outer section cell bracket
in this notebook
closes the section cells
to show only the section headings,
which gives this outline overview
of the notebook.
For many projects,
it is convenient to start
with an outline like this
and then proceed with the project
by entering content
within that outline.
Closed cells can be reopened
by double-clicking
on the same cell bracket
or by clicking this icon
in the heading of the closed cell.
Notebooks support
many other formatting features.
So far, this notebook has only
been shown with the default styles.
But the notebook can be displayed
in a variety of formats
by choosing from
different stylesheets,
like the ones shown here,
or by setting up your own styles.
Another important feature
of notebooks
is support
for mathematical typesetting,
which is useful for projects that
involve any sort of mathematics.
The default mathematical typesetting
will look more like this,
with slightly different typeface
and formatting,
which has some advantages,
or there are options
to make the display
look more like what you might find
in a traditional textbook.
All of this is fully integrated
with the rest of the system,
and can be used for input or output
or anywhere else in a notebook.
You can also create tables
and itemized lists
and automatic numbering
and other structures
that you might expect to find
in a modern typesetting system.
Notebooks also support
interactive controls,
like buttons and sliders.
Here, for example, is a display
that provides sliders
for selecting a range
of earthquake magnitudes
and buttons for selecting
the year.
Controls like these can be used
to set up interactive documents
so that anyone using the notebook
can explore data
or choose the content
that they want to see
or even control
complicated calculations
right from within the notebook.
As noted earlier,
there are a number of ways
of sharing notebooks
or saving notebooks to the cloud.
Under the File menu,
you can choose save to cloud
and then reload the notebook
from the cloud,
or here I will choose
publish to cloud,
which saves a notebook that
can be viewed in any web browser.
This shows that notebook
in a web browser,
where the notebook
looks and behaves
much like the original notebook,
including all
of the interactive features.
So, this is a dynamic document.
Notebooks can also be shared
just as they are,
as electronic documents,
and viewed using any
Wolfram Language system,
or using the free
Wolfram Notebook player.
This shows that notebook viewed
in the Wolfram Player,
which again behaves much like
the original notebook,
except for a different border
around the window.
With a few clicks of the mouse,
this notebook can also
be converted to a slideshow,
with each section
in a separate slide.
For this notebook,
that can be done
by setting the style sheet
to a PresenterTools style,
and then setting the screen
environment to Slideshow Working,
to access the tools
for editing the presentation.
One of those tools
brings up this dialog box
to get a separate slide
for each section.
Then click Start Presentation
to show the slides.
All of the editing and interactive
features work in the presentation
just as they do
in the original notebook.
So basically, Wolfram Notebooks
provide a system for organizing
projects and collaboration,
all the way from initial concept
through to distribution of reports
or presentations
or sharing in the cloud
or even as Wolfram Language
expressions embedded in code.
There is much more to be said
about all of the features
that came up in this short video.
You can find more information
in online documentation
or in other videos
on Wolfram Notebooks.