This section is about
customizing the overall style
of Wolfram Notebooks
and the styles of the cells
and the content
within a notebook.
Style here refers
to the appearance
and behavior of things
in a notebook.
For example,
here is a typical notebook,
which like all Wolfram Notebooks
is made up of units called cells,
which are identified
by these brackets
on the right side of the window.
Cells have different styles.
The first cell
has a style called Title,
the style of the second cell
is Section
and this notebook also contains
two Text cells
and two Input cells
and two Output cells.
Each cell style
uses different colors
and different fonts
and font sizes.
Text cells use different
indentation than Section cells,
and Input and Output cells
have these labels
with the input
and output number.
All of these things are part
of the style of the cell.
A notebook like this
can be created
by choosing New
from the File menu
to get a new notebook, and
typing into the empty notebook.
Input by default
goes into an Input Cell
and if I evaluate that input
the result is displayed
in an Output cell.
Subsequent inputs and outputs
give additional Input
and Output cells.
The horizontal line
after the last output
is the Cell Insertion Bar.
This is where a new cell
will appear if I start typing.
To put a cell somewhere else,
I can click to position
the cell insertion bar
anywhere between
the existing cells.
The available cell styles
for this notebook
are shown in the Style submenu
of the Format menu.
For example, to add a Title cell
I can click to position
the cell insertion bar
at the top of the notebook,
choose title from the Style
submenu and enter the title.
To enter the Section Cell,
I will choose Section
from the Style submenu
and enter the name
of the section.
Common cell styles
also have keyboard shortcuts,
which are listed
in the Style submenu.
For example, to add a Text cell
I will here use
the keyboard shortcut
and then enter the contents
of the cell.
The style of a cell can also be
changed after the cell is created.
For example,
to insert another Text cell
I can position
the cell insertion bar
where I want the new cell and
enter the contents of the cell.
Right now, this is an Input cell,
since that is the default,
but I can convert it
to a Text cell
by choosing Text
from the Style submenu
or by typing
the keyboard shortcut,
and the cell is converted
to a Text cell.
Actually if I just start typing
ordinary text into an Input cell,
like this, the system
typically recognizes that
whatever is being entered
is not computer input
and puts up this menu
offering to treat the input
in some other way.
One of the choices
on that menu is text,
which converts the cell
into a Text cell,
so that is yet another way
to get a Text cell.
Almost everything in this display
can be customized.
For example,
to emphasize some bit of text,
I could select that text
and change the style
using items
under the Format menu.
For example,
this sets the text color to red
and the text
to a somewhat larger size.
You can also change
the styles for entire cells.
For example, to change the styles
for the Section cell
I can select the cell bracket
and again use items
from the Format menu
to change the styles.
For example,
this sets the background
of the cell to light orange
and the text color to black.
All of these changes work
by controlling options
in the underlying
cell expressions.
You can see
the options settings explicitly
by choosing Show Expression
from the Cell menu,
which displays
the underlying cell expression.
For example,
with that Section cell selected
I can choose Show Expression
to see the cell expression,
which shows the content
of the cell
and the argument that identifies
this as a Section cell
and the font color option
to specify that the text
should be shown in black
and the background option
to specify
the light orange background.
This particular RGB
color expression
is how colors are specified
in notebooks.
I can also type options
into the cell directly.
For example, here I will insert
the TextAlignment option
and specify Center
as the value of the option.
Then choose Show Expression
from the Cell menu
to reformat the cell
and the display shows the effect
of all of those options settings,
including the effect
of the TextAlignment option
to center the text.
There are actually many hundreds
of options like this.
The general tool for setting
options is the Option Inspector,
which is opened
by choosing Option Inspector
from the Format menu or by using
the equivalent keyboard shortcut.
For example, entering background
into the search box
in the Option Inspector
brings up the entry
for the Background option,
which here shows
the value of this option
that was just entered
using the Format menu.
The icon with the X
on the left side
of the Option Inspector entry
indicates that this option
is set within the selection.
Clicking that icon
removes that option setting,
which returns the background
to the default value,
which for this cell
is a plain white background.
You can also enter
options settings
using the Option Inspector.
For example, there is an option
called CellDingbat
that can be used to add
something called a cell dingbat,
which is a kind of marker
on the left side of the cell.
Clicking this little arrow
brings up a menu of choices
for the cell dingbat.
Here I will choose
Filled Small Circle,
which changes the value
of the option
in the Option Inspector
and adds a filled small circle
on the left side of the cell.
In the upper left corner
of the Option Inspector
there is another important menu
for choosing whether options
should be shown
for the thing that is selected
or for the entire
selected notebook,
or if the Option Inspector
should show global preferences.
For example,
choosing Selected Notebook
causes the Option Inspector
to show options
for the entire notebook,
not just for the selected cell.
For example, if I now set
the background option
to some other color,
that will set the background
for the entire notebook
and not just
for the selected cell.
For now I will click the X
in the Option Inspector
to set the background color
back to the default.
Rather than setting options for
individual selections like this,
probably the most common way
of customizing a notebook
is by choosing from
predefined cell styles
and predefined stylesheets.
Every notebook has a stylesheet.
The stylesheet for a notebook
can be set
by choosing a stylesheet
from the Stylesheet submenu
under the Format menu.
This particular notebook
uses a stylesheet called Default,
which is the item
that is checked in this menu.
All of the options for the cells
in this notebook
are set up in that stylesheet.
There are quite a few other
stylesheets to choose from.
For example,
this switches the stylesheet
for this notebook
to JournalArticle.
This is still the same notebook,
but the display uses
different fonts
and different font sizes
and the title is centered
rather than aligned on the left
and there are
many other differences.
Here is another stylesheet
called Garnet
from the PresenterTools submenu.
PresenterTools styles are styles
that can be used to show
this notebook as a slideshow,
which will be discussed
in a later section.
That's the end of the examples
for this section.
The next section
is about editing stylesheets,
which you can do
to customize existing styles
or create new cell styles
or to design your own stylesheets.
There are also hundreds
of cell options
and notebook options
beyond the options
that came up in this section.
You can find more information
about other options
in the Wolfram Documentation
in this tutorial
on Options for Cells
and in this tutorial
on Options for Notebooks.