This section of Introduction
to Wolfram Notebooks
is about customizing the style
of a notebook
by editing stylesheets.
The stylesheet is where all
of the cell styles
and things like indentation
and font sizes
and background colors and so on
are specified for cells
and for the notebook.
Every notebook has a stylesheet.
The stylesheet can be chosen
from the Stylesheet submenu
under the Format menu.
This notebook was created
by just selecting new notebook
from the File menu
without specifying a stylesheet,
so the notebook was assigned
a stylesheet called Default,
which is the item
that is checked in this menu,
but there are lots of other
stylesheets to choose from.
For example, this chooses
the Sky stylesheet
from the PresenterTools submenu.
PresenterTools styles are used
for showing the notebook
as a slideshow,
as will be discussed
in a later section.
You can also select
Stylesheet Chooser
from the Style menu,
which opens this palette
for selecting a stylesheet.
The lower part of each item
in this display
is used to apply that style
to an existing notebook
and the upper part
creates a new notebook.
For example,
here I will click the upper part
of the entry
for a StandardReport style,
which gives a notebook that uses
the StandardReport stylesheet,
and in addition, that notebook
is already filled in
with examples
of all of the cell styles
that are defined
within that stylesheet,
which is a nice way
of getting an overview
of what the available
cell styles look like.
Even with lots
of possible stylesheets
and cell styles to choose from,
there are still situations where
it is useful to customize things,
which you can do
by editing the stylesheet.
To show an example
of how that can work,
I will return this notebook
to the default stylesheet
and choose Edit Stylesheet
from the Format menu.
The stylesheet that comes up
is not the default stylesheet,
but rather a private stylesheet
that is specific to this notebook.
This private stylesheet
can be used
to specify option settings
to apply in preference
to the settings
in the actual
default stylesheet.
For example,
to change the styles
for all of the text cells
in the notebook,
I will start by choosing Text
from the Choose a style menu,
which generates here
a special type of cell
that is mostly only used
in stylesheets.
The other items at the top
of this window
are the Enter a style name box,
which can be used to introduce
a new cell style
and the Install Stylesheet button,
which is used to add
a whole new stylesheet
that can be used
by other notebooks.
Any option settings that I add
for this new cell
in the stylesheet
will apply to all of
the text cells in the notebook.
For example,
here I will select this cell
and use items
under the Format menu
to set the background color
to light orange
and set an italic font.
Choosing Show Expression
from the cell menu
shows the underlying
cell expression,
with the new settings
for the background option
and the font slant option.
What makes this cell special
is that the content of the cell
is this style data expression.
The stylesheet itself
is a notebook
and in general a stylesheet
is just a notebook
where all of the cells are
these special style data cells.
Returning to
the original notebook
shows that this change
in the stylesheet
had the effect of changing
the background color
and the font slant
for all of the text cells
in the notebook.
It is still possible to override
the styles in the stylesheet
by making changes directly
to selections in a notebook.
For example,
if I don't want the italic font
for some part of the text,
I can select that text
and specify a different font.
When a style is specified
in several different places
like the italic font
in this text cell,
the general principle
is that styles that are set
for a specific selection
take precedence over settings
in a stylesheet.
That general principle
is also sometimes described
using the notion of inheritance.
We could say, for example,
that any style not explicitly
specified in the notebook
is inherited from
the stylesheet.
There is also a principle of
inheritance for the stylesheets,
since most notebooks
actually use
a sequence of stylesheets.
For example, returning to
the private stylesheet,
at the top of the stylesheet
is a cell that says
that styles here are inherited
from the default stylesheet.
Clicking on the hyperlink
in that cell
brings up the actual
default stylesheet,
which includes specifications
not just for text cells,
but for all of the cell styles
within this stylesheet.
The default stylesheet
also includes a cell at the top,
noting that this stylesheet
inherits styles
from another stylesheet
called Core,
which is the end
of the sequence.
Any style not specified
in one of these stylesheets
just uses a global value.
Inheritance for this set
of stylesheets
means that each stylesheet
inherits styles
from the stylesheet above it.
Usually the only stylesheet to
edit is the private stylesheet
for the notebook,
but it is often useful to see
what is in one
of the other stylesheets.
For example, one of the styles
in this stylesheet is Item style,
which can be used
for creating bullet lists
like this one,
but suppose that I want
to add a new style
that works just like Item style
except that the marker,
the cell dingbat for each cell,
is a checkmark
rather than a filled square
and the text is shown
in bold letters.
If I do that by going
to the private stylesheet
and choosing Item style,
I will be modifying
the default Item style,
but here I want to leave
the default Item style alone
and instead create
a new cell style,
which I will do by going through
the default stylesheet
and navigating to the cell
in this stylesheet
that describes Item cells,
where I will select
the cell bracket for that cell
to select the entire cell,
then copy the cell
and return to
the private stylesheet
for this notebook
and paste that cell
into the private stylesheet.
The difference between this cell
and the one above it
can be seen by showing
the cell expressions.
The second cell here,
which is the one that
I just copied from
the default stylesheet,
includes all of the option
settings for Item cells.
So even when I change
the name of the cell,
which will have the effect
of creating a new cell style,
the new cell style
will still behave
exactly like an Item cell.
The default CellDingbat
is the FilledSmallSquare,
which I will change now
to the Checkmark character.
I will also change the value
of the MenuSortingValue option
to a smaller number.
This isn't a critical change,
but it will have the effect
of moving the new cell style
to the top of the style menu,
where it will be easier to find.
There are several
other options here,
which won't be explored here,
except to note that one good way
to learn about options
is to find a cell style
and then look in the stylesheet
to see the options that were used
to set up that style.
I could change the font
to a bold font
by typing in the option here,
but I will instead do that
by reformatting the cell
and choosing Bold
from the Face item
under the Format menu.
Now return to
the original notebook
and add a cell
by choosing the new
CheckmarkItem style
from the Style menu,
which adds a new cell
that behaves like an item cell
except for the checkmark
cell dingbat and the bold font.
Before concluding the subject
of stylesheets,
many stylesheets support
variations that can be selected
by specifying an option
called Environment.
For example,
the current environment
for displaying this notebook
on the computer screen
is called Working environment,
which we can see
because Working is checked
in the Screen Environment submenu
under the Format menu.
If the screen environment
is changed to Printout,
the styles used in the notebook
change to styles
that are more appropriate
for printing.
In this example,
switching to Printout environment
changes the magnification
and the cell margins
and limits the page width
to the width of printing paper.
The different environments could,
in principle,
give cells with completely
different sets of options
and completely different styles,
but environments
are more typically used
to introduce small variations
on a general theme,
like optimizing a notebook
for printing
or optimizing a notebook
for a slide presentation.
There is really an enormous range
of other things
that can be done like this
to customize notebook styles.
You can find more information
about stylesheets
in the Wolfram Documentation
by navigating to this tutorial
on working with stylesheets
and a good reference
on the general structure
of Wolfram notebooks
is this section on notebooks
as Wolfram Language expressions.