This section of Introduction
to Wolfram Notebooks
is about making notebooks
into interactive documents
and more specifically
about setting up tools,
like the buttons
in this first example
for navigating through data
or linking to other documents,
and features, like the sliders
in this second example
that provide interactive controls
for running programs
and doing calculations
for within a notebook.
Probably the most common
interactive feature
of modern documents
is a simple hyperlink,
which is typically a link
to another document.
For example, here is a notebook
with gross domestic product
or GDP data for a group of
seven countries called the G7.
In this notebook
G7 is a hyperlink,
which has been set up
so that clicking that link
brings up a webpage.
Hyperlinks can be created
using the Hyperlink button
from the Insert menu.
For example, to create
a hyperlink for the term GDP,
select GDP in the notebook,
then choose Hyperlink
from the Insert menu,
which brings up a dialog box
where I can enter
the destination of the link.
For this example, I will enter
a web address and click OK,
and after that
clicking GDP in the notebook
opens that webpage.
Hyperlinks are a common way
of organizing sets
of related documents
so that users of the documents
can follow hyperlinks
to the information
that they want to see.
For example, this notebook
is arranged in sections.
So to see information
on one of the countries,
I can scroll through the notebook
and open a section,
but the information
in each section
could also have been organized
with a separate notebook
for each section,
like the notebook shown here
and linked to the original
notebook using hyperlinks.
To create one
of those hyperlinks,
I will start in
the original notebook,
select the name of a country,
open the hyperlink dialog box
and click the Browse button
to open the file browser,
where I will choose a notebook
as the destination of the link.
Returning to
the original notebook,
the selected text
is now a hyperlink
that I can click
to open the other notebook.
Organizing information into
a set of hyperlinked notebooks
is especially useful
in more complex projects,
where documents might come
from different sources
or be created
by different people.
This hyperlink will only work
on a computer that
also has all
of the linked notebooks,
but the linked notebook could
also have been saved in the cloud
so that the hyperlink would work
on any computer
that is connected to the cloud.
For example,
here is another notebook
where I will choose
Publish to Cloud
to make the notebook
available in the cloud.
Then copy the URL
for use in the hyperlink
and create a hyperlink as before,
using the hyperlink dialog box.
Clicking that hyperlink
opens the saved notebook
in a web browser.
So that is a way
of setting up linked documents
that will work on any computer
that is connected to the cloud.
You can also use hyperlinks
to navigate within a notebook.
Hyperlinks within a notebook
work primarily by linking
to tagged cells.
To add a tag for a cell,
I can select the cell
and choose Add/Remove Cell Tags
from the Cell Tag submenu
under the Cell menu,
which brings up this dialog box
where I can enter a tag.
After entering the tag,
click the Add button
to add that tag,
and then set up
the hyperlink as before
using the hyperlink dialog box.
In the dialog box,
I will click the button
to use cells with the selected
tag as the destination.
Choose a tag and click OK
to create the hyperlink.
Clicking that hyperlink
jumps to the tagged cell
within this notebook.
Another way
of setting up navigation
through the information
in a notebook
is with tools called views.
The basic idea is illustrated
by this example,
which shows a function
called TabView
that provides a row of buttons
for displaying different images.
The same system can also be used
to display the information
in this notebook.
For example,
here is a TabView input
that gives a display
with a row of buttons,
that can be clicked to
display data for each country.
There are several other functions
like the TabView function.
For example, this shows
a function called MenuView
that gives a menu
instead of a row of buttons.
Views can also be nested.
For example,
this shows a TabView
in which each displayed
expression is another tab view,
which is used here
for selecting a pair of countries
to include in the plot.
The best way of setting up
interactive navigation
through a document
depends, of course,
on what is in the document
and on who will be using it,
but all of these functions
have lots of options
and in the documentation
there are good tutorials
and lots of examples for learning
about the possibilities.
So far the examples
have mostly involved navigating
through a fixed set
of information,
but notebooks can also include
buttons and sliders
and other controls
for controlling programs
and doing calculations.
One tool for setting up
controls like that
is the Manipulate function.
Here is a simple Manipulate input
that gives a result with a slider
for adjusting the frequency
of a sine wave in a plot.
Here is the example
that was shown earlier.
This example is
a little more complicated,
but the basic idea is the same.
The first argument in Manipulate
gives the calculation to do
and the result to display
and the other arguments
specify the controls.
The calculation in this example
involves plotting
a numerical solution
of a differential equation,
and there are two sliders
for adjusting parameters
in the differential equation.
The sliders in that result
use a general system
for dynamically
updating calculations
whenever there is a change
in a parameter
that is used in that calculation.
Normally if a parameter
is used in a calculation,
such as the parameter x
in this plot,
the calculation
does not get redone
if the parameter is changed.
This plot, for example,
does not get regenerated
if I change the value of x.
To get a result that will be
dynamically updated,
I can enclose the result
in Dynamic.
Unlike the previous output,
this plot does change whenever
the value of x is changed.
One way of changing the value
of x is with a slider.
For example,
this input gives a slider
for setting the value of x
to a number between 0 and 10.
The Dynamic function
is used in the slider input
to indicate that changes
should cause automatic updating.
The result is a slider
that controls the plot.
Wolfram Notebooks support
a variety of controls
other than sliders.
For example, here is a control
called an Animator
for continuously updating
the value of a parameter.
Here is another control
called a RadioButtonBar
that gives a row of buttons
for setting the value of x.
Another common
interactive control is a menu.
This input gives a pop-up menu
for setting the value of x.
Interactive features like these
can be useful
for illustrating concepts
or to allow someone
using the document
to do their own calculations.
For example,
this shows a modified version
of the earlier
Manipulate example,
this time including
an animation of a corresponding
mechanical system.
Interactive illustrations like
this are often quite helpful
for explaining
complicated topics.
The programming for this example
has been hidden
by closing the cell group.
I can double-click
on the cell bracket
to open the cell group
and show the input
that produced this result.
Most of the programming
is associated
with constructing
the images in the display.
The controls are specified
in just a few lines
of code at the end.
This last specification,
for example,
is the code that creates
this control, called a Trigger,
that initiates the animation.
These controls also work
in the cloud.
For example, this first input
generates a list
of the components
of the Dow Jones
Industrial Average
and after that,
here is a Manipulate
for plotting closing prices
of those components.
The control in this result
is a menu for choosing
the component to plot.
Rather than choosing
Publish to Cloud
from the File menu
to publish this entire notebook,
this time I will use
the CloudPublish function
to publish
just the Manipulate output.
The result is a link that
I could send to other people
or that here,
I will enter into a web browser
to show a notebook with that
same interactive display.
This result is similar
in appearance
to the MenuView example
shown earlier,
but making a choice
in this result
causes a new plot to be generated
using current data
rather than selecting
from pre-existing plots.
So this is a good approach
for sharing documents
with information
that might change.
That's the end of the examples
for the section.
You can find more information
on View functions,
like TabView and MenuView,
in the Wolfram documentation
by searching for views
and navigating to this page
on view functions.
For information on Manipulate,
a good place to start
is the documentation
for the Manipulate function.
There are also several tutorials
on Manipulate
and on controls in general,
and this guide page
on control objects
lists all of the various controls
like the sliders and popup menus
and other controls
that came up in this section.