This section of Introduction
to Wolfram Notebooks
is about formatting things
like tables and matrices
and bullet lists.
Starting with bullet lists,
one easy way to get a bullet
or itemized list
is to choose Item
from the Style submenu
under the Format menu,
to get an Item cell
and then enter
the contents of the cell.
Item cells have the property
that pressing the RETURN key
from within an Item cell
generates a new Item cell,
so items can be added
just by typing RETURN.
There is also
a keyboard shortcut
for creating an Item cell,
which is to type an asterisk
to create a new cell.
For example,
with the cell insertion bar
where it is now,
the input would, by default,
become an Input cell.
But if I type an asterisk
as the first character,
then the cell becomes
an Item cell.
So that is a way to enter
an itemized list
directly from the keyboard,
without using the menus.
Numbered lists can be created
by choosing ItemNumbered
from the Style submenu
and proceeding much as before.
The number is incremented
automatically for each new entry.
The number in those numbered
items is the cell dingbat.
A cell dingbat in general
is just a marker
on the left side of the cell.
The numbering, however, can
actually be inserted anywhere.
For example, to get
automatically numbered sections,
I can enter a section heading
and insert a number,
by positioning the entry point
where I want to put the number
and choosing Automatic Numbering
from the Insert menu,
which brings up a dialog box
that I can use to insert a number
that will be incremented
for each new section cell.
I can insert more
numbered sections
by making a copy of that cell
and pasting it
wherever I want
a new numbered section,
and the number will be
incremented automatically
for each section.
You can find more information
about automatic numbering
in the Wolfram documentation
in this tutorial
on automatic numbering
and in the documentation
for the Automatic Numbering
menu item.
Moving on now
to creating tables and matrices,
an easy way to get a matrix is
to choose the Table/Matrix item
under the Insert menu.
Choosing New from the submenu
brings up this dialog box,
where I can set various options
and choose the number of rows
and the number of columns.
Here I will click the button
to give a matrix
and specify 3 rows and 3 columns
and then click the OK button
to get a 3-by-3 matrix
in the notebook.
The elements in that matrix
are empty boxes
called placeholders,
where I can enter
matrix elements.
I will use the mouse
to select the first placeholder
and enter a value,
then use the Tab key to move
to the next placeholder
and enter the next value,
then use the Tab key again
to move to the next placeholder
and enter the next value
and so on for the rest
of the matrix.
The Add Row and Add Column items
in the Table/Matrix submenu
can be used to add rows
and columns to this matrix.
To do that,
I will click on the matrix
to select where I want to enter
a row or a column
and then choose the Add Row
or Add Column menu items.
Those menu items
also have keyboard shortcuts.
CONTROL+RETURN
creates a new row
and CONTROL+COMMA
creates a new column,
and those keyboard shortcuts
actually can also be used
outside of a matrix
to create a new matrix.
For example,
if I press CONTROL+RETURN
in a place that isn't part
of a current matrix,
the effect is to generate a new
matrix with one placeholder
and add a row to that matrix,
which gives a matrix
with two rows and one column.
Additional rows and columns
can then be created
by pressing CONTROL+RETURN
to add rows
and CONTROL+COMMA
to add columns,
so it is possible to create
a matrix entirely
using keyboard commands,
without ever going to the menus.
The system for formatting
a matrix can also be used
to format a table
like this one.
Start by choosing Table/Matrix
from the Insert menu
and click New
to bring up the dialog box.
This time I will select
the Table button.
I also want lines
between the rows
and lines between the columns
and a frame around the table,
so I will check all
of those boxes
and click OK to get the table.
I could have specified
a 6x5 table in the dialog box,
but instead I will select
an element in the table
and use CONTROL+RETURN
and CONTROL+COMMA
to add rows and columns.
Several of the entries
in the desired table
span more than one row
or more than one column.
To get those spanning entries,
I will select the entries
that are to be merged
and choose Make Spanning
from the Table/Matrix menu
and repeat that process for
the other elements that are
combined in this table.
All that remains now
is to enter values
for the elements in the table,
but if I just start typing,
all of the inputs
are treated as variables
or as other
Wolfram Language commands,
which happens because
this is still an Input cell
and input into an Input cell
is treated by default
as Wolfram Language commands.
Sometimes that is fine,
but since much of this table
is plain text,
it might be better
to have text be the default.
One way to make that happen
is to change the style
of this cell from Input to Text,
and as long as I am changing
the styles of things,
I will also change the font
using the Show Fonts dialog box.
Now proceed with filling in
the entries in the table.
It is worth noting
that this is still a live table
that could have been generated
or filled in automatically,
and the table
and parts of the table
can be used as data
in other computations.
For example, I can copy
some desired part of the table
and paste that
into the Total function
to get the sum of the amounts
in that part of the table.
There is much more
that can be done
with the formatting of tables,
some of which is introduced
in the next section,
and you can also find
more information
in the Wolfram Documentation,
starting with this short tutorial
on entering tables and matrices
using the Table/Matrix menu item.
And you can also follow
links to this guide
to all of the functions
and options
related to grids and tables.