This section of Introduction
to Wolfram Notebooks
describes a more precise tools
for formatting tables,
like the table shown here,
and is specifically about options
for setting up details,
like the horizontal divider
and the rows
with alternating backgrounds,
and tools for controlling
the appearance
of individual items in a table.
Starting with the first example,
here is an input that generates
a template for that table.
Evaluating this input
gives a result in an Output cell,
which I will convert
to a Text cell,
since most of the entries
in that table are plain text.
The input uses the Grid function.
The first argument
of the Grid function
is the actual array
of table entries
that gives the headings
and an array of placeholders,
and there are six options.
The Background option
sets up the alternating
white and gray backgrounds
for the rows.
If I click inside the table
and use CONTROL+RETURN
to add more rows,
the alternating backgrounds
continue for the new rows.
The Alignment option specifies
the horizontal alignment
of entries within each column
and vertical alignment
within each row.
The Dividers option
draws the lines between the rows.
This is where
the thick horizontal divider
below the heading is specified.
The BaseStyle option
specifies the font to use
for entries in the table.
And finally, the ItemSize option
specifies the space
to allow for each column,
and the Spacings option
specifies space between columns.
There are lots of details
that these options control,
but the basic ideas
are fairly simple
and several of these options
use similar designs
that can be illustrated
by considering their effect
on a generic table.
Here is a table
with placeholder entries
and with Frame set to All
to make it easier
to see the rows and the columns.
Starting with
the Background option,
the Background option
can be set to a single color,
to set the background
for the entire grid,
but the general form
of the Background option
is a list with three elements
where the first element
specifies the background
for columns,
the second element
specifies the background for rows
and the third element
can be used to specify
the background for individual
elements in the table.
For example,
entering Red, Green, Blue
in the first element
causes the first three columns
to be red, green and blue.
Enclosing colors in a list
causes those colors
to be repeated across the table.
For example, this gives red
for the first column
and repeated green
and blue columns
for the rest of the table.
The same structure
applies to rows.
For example,
if that same color specification
is the second element
in the value
of the Background option,
the result is a table
where the first row is red
and the remaining rows alternate
between green and blue.
The third element in the value
of the Background option
can be used for specifying
the background color
of individual entries
in the table.
For example, this specifies
that the seventh element
in the fourth row
should have
an orange background.
Similar principles apply
to the Dividers option
and to the Alignment option
and to all of the options
that control specific
rows and columns.
For example, this shows a value
for the Dividers option
that gives a column divider
every third column
and a row divider
above the second row.
As with the Background option,
the value of the Dividers option
is a list.
The first element of that list
specifies column dividers
and the second element
specifies row dividers.
The dividers
can also have styles.
For example, this specifies
that the column dividers
should be repeated
thick lines and light gray lines,
and that the horizontal divider
below the top row
should be a thick red line.
With those general
principles in mind,
here again is the first example,
where I will go ahead and fill in
some values in the table.
This value
of the Background option
gives the alternating
white and light gray background
for the rows.
The Alignment option specifies
that items in the first column
should be centered horizontally.
The second column
should be aligned on the right,
as is typically done
for columns of numbers
and items in the third column
are aligned on the left.
This value of the Dividers option
gives the thick line
below the top row
and the light gray dividers
for all of the rows after that.
The light gray divider
becomes part of the background
for all of the rows
except the last one,
where the divider shows up
as a light grey line
at the bottom of the table.
The BaseStyle option
specifies the default font
to use for all of the items
in the table.
The ItemSize option here
specifies the width
of each column.
The first two columns
are given as scaled amounts,
which means that they are scaled
to a fraction
of the formatting width,
which is related to the width
of the window.
So the width
of the columns changes
with the width of the display,
which can be desirable
if the table might be displayed
in different windows.
Finally, this value
of the Spacings option
adds some space
between the last two columns.
A good way to learn
what these options do
is to try different values
for the options
and observe the effect
on the table.
For example, here is a simple
Manipulate program
that gives a control
for adjusting the space
between the last two columns.
Rather than using options
for the Grid function,
a separate strategy
for specifying styles
is to use Item expressions
as elements in the table
and to specify options
within each Item expression.
For example, rather than using
the Background option
to specify the background color
of a particular entry
in the table,
another way to get
the same effect
is to make that one element
into an Item expression
and to include
the Background option
in that Item expression.
A related feature
is using the special symbols
SpanFromLeft, SpanFromAbove
and SpanFromBoth
to get table entries that span
more than one row
or more than one column.
For example, here is
a small table of placeholders.
Replacing one
of those placeholders
with the special symbol
SpanFromLeft
causes that entry in the table
to be merged
with the entry to the left.
There are also symbols
called SpanFromAbove
and SpanFromBoth
that can be used to merge entries
vertically or in both directions.
The affect actually ends up
being the same
as selecting items to be merged
and choosing Make Spanning
from the Table/Matrix submenu.
As a final example which uses
several of these tools,
here is the second
of the two tables
that were shown earlier
together with an input
to generate that table.
This input again
uses the Grid function
with several options.
The ItemSize option
specifies columns
with a width of three,
which means
three units called ems.
An em is a unit
equal to the point size
of the current font.
If the ItemSize option
is omitted,
then the columns are adjusted
to the width of the widest item
in the column,
which here gives a table
with columns
that seem a bit too narrow,
so the ItemSize option
is included
to give a table
that is not quite so cramped.
This value of the Frame option
draws the divider lines
and the frame around the table.
This value of the Alignment option
specifies that
items should be centered
both vertically and horizontally
and the Background option
specifies a light gray background
for the top row
and alternating orange
and light blue background,
for the remaining rows.
Background is used in this table
as a color code for the T
and F entries in the table.
The Background option
happens in this example
to give the correct color
for all of the entries,
except for one
where the background is specified
in an Item expression.
Without that Item expression,
the color for that item
would be light blue,
which doesn't follow
the intended color code.
This table also includes
two SpanFromAbove entries,
which are there to generate
the two items in the first column
that span more than one row.
That's the end of the examples
for this section.
A good source
for additional information
is the documentation
for the Grid function
and related functions,
and especially this tutorial
on grids, rows and columns.
And it is of course
almost always useful
to just construct a generic table
and try these things out
for yourself.