This section of Introduction
to Wolfram Notebooks
is about using notebooks
on different platforms,
especially in the cloud
and on mobile devices
like tablets and smartphones.
For example, here is a notebook
shown on a tablet computer
and displayed using
the free Wolfram Player app.
With this app you can
scroll through the notebook
and open and close cells
by double tapping
on cell grouping brackets,
much as in Wolfram Desktop.
And the notebook
can also be a dynamic document,
so for example, you can adjust
the controls of dynamic content
like the buttons and the slider
in this Manipulate result.
The interactive controls
in the Wolfram Player app
are shown at the bottom
of the screen,
which is done because
the controls on a mobile device
are typically manipulated
using finger taps
rather than with a mouse,
and fingers can block the display.
So having the controls
at the bottom of the screen
can make it easier
to see the display
and operate the controls
at the same time.
To create or edit a notebook,
instead of Wolfram Player,
you can use
the Wolfram Cloud app.
For example, this shows
that same notebook
in the Wolfram Cloud app,
which includes controls
for editing the notebook.
Those controls are used here
for inserting a new Text cell.
Editing will be described
in more detail in a moment.
The Wolfram Player
and the Wolfram Cloud apps
also work on smartphones.
Here, for example,
is that notebook
on a smartphone,
using the Wolfram Player app.
Except for the size
of the screen,
the display works
much as it does on the tablet,
including dynamic content
like buttons and sliders.
Notebooks can also be displayed
and edited in a web browser
on any computer that is connected
to the internet
or to a suitable cloud.
For example, this shows
that notebook in a web browser
on a desktop computer
through a web page
that is logged into
a free Wolfram Cloud account.
Interactive controls
work here as well
and the notebook can be edited,
such as adding a new text cell,
and you can do calculations.
And of course
the notebook can also be shown
in an ordinary
desktop application.
This, for example,
shows that notebook
on a desktop computer
running Wolfram Desktop.
The underlying notebook file
is the same on all
of these platforms,
on a mobile device
or in a web browser
or on the desktop,
and the same notebook
can be opened in any platform.
For example, starting with
this notebook on the desktop,
you can choose Save to Cloud
to save the notebook
in a cloud account.
If the desktop application
is not already signed in
to Wolfram Cloud Account,
you will be asked to sign in,
and after that
you can choose a name
for saving the notebook
in that account.
The notebook in the cloud
can be opened
in any of these platforms.
For example,
returning to the tablet,
after installing
the Wolfram Player app
you can launch
the app, which shows
the notebooks that are saved
on this device,
but to see the notebook
that was just uploaded
to the cloud,
you can tap the button in the
upper-left corner of the screen
to open the side panel,
tap Add Cloud Account
and use the dialog box
to log into that cloud account.
The notebook that was
just saved to the cloud
was saved in the home directory
of that account,
so navigate to that directory
and open the notebook.
There are buttons in the upper-
right corner of this window
for various operations
with this notebook.
Tapping the button
with letters on it
opens a small dialog box
that is used here to make
the display a little bit bigger,
which results in the display
that was shown earlier.
This notebook currently exists
in the cloud,
but you can also save
the notebook locally
on this tablet computer
by tapping this button
in the upper-right corner
of the window,
which opens a dialog box
with various choices.
To save the notebook
on this tablet,
tap Save to Files,
which opens a dialog box
for choosing where
to save the notebook.
With the notebook saved
on this tablet,
you could sign out
of the cloud account
and even disconnect
from the internet
and still view the notebook.
The basic programs for
interacting with this notebook
are all running locally
on this tablet,
which makes these operations
significantly faster,
since it avoids the overhead
of running over the internet,
and dynamic content like buttons
and sliders will also work.
Working without being connected
to the internet, of course,
requires that nothing
in these operations
either directly or indirectly
tries to access the internet.
In this particular notebook,
the earthquake data, for example,
has to be included
in the notebook.
To edit the notebook
still on the tablet,
you can start by launching
the Wolfram Cloud app.
After logging into the account,
you can tap to open the notebook.
The display includes
the same font magnification
button as the Wolfram Player app.
Editing the notebook
to insert a new cell
starts much as it does
on the desktop
by clicking, or in this case
tapping, to get
a cell insertion bar,
which also brings up
a row of buttons
at the bottom of the screen.
To enter a calculation,
tap the Input cell button,
which creates a new Input cell
and also brings up
a special keyboard
for entering input.
You can use the keyboard
to enter the input
and then tap the evaluate button
to do the calculation.
To get a Text cell,
tap the new cell button
and choose Plain Text,
which creates a Text cell
and opens a keyboard
for entering the contents
of the cell.
Other types of cells
can be entered
by choosing Styled Text
from the new cell menu.
For example,
you can choose Section
to get a Section cell
and then enter the contents
of the cell.
Selecting cell brackets
brings up a different row
of buttons
for copying or pasting
or cutting cells.
For example, this shows
using the Cut button
to delete the cells
that were just entered.
Finally as was shown earlier,
Wolfram Notebooks
can also be edited
using a web browser.
You can start
at the Wolfram Cloud website.
Log in to your
Wolfram Cloud Account
and navigate to the notebook
that you want to edit.
Here you can enter calculations
by clicking in the notebook
to get a cell insertion bar,
enter the calculation
using the keyboard
and press SHIFT+ENTER
to do the calculation.
Many features of Wolfram Desktop
are also available here,
including, for example,
the Suggestions Bar
below the output.
Keyboard shortcuts can be used
for choosing new cell styles.
For example, you can type
the keyboard shortcut
for a new Text cell
and enter the contents
of the cell.
Another way of choosing
the style of a new cell
is to click the Format button
at the top of the window,
which opens a side panel
with controls for choosing fonts
and cell styles and so on.
For example,
to get a Section cell,
you can choose Section
from the Cell Style menu
and enter the contents
of the cell.
For just getting started
with Wolfram Notebooks,
Wolfram Cloud is in some ways
the easiest place to begin,
because usually
there's nothing to install.
All you need is a web browser
on a computer
connected to the internet.
For example,
you can open a web browser
and go to the Wolfram webpage,
www.wolfram.com,
which shows the whole range
of products.
One of those products
is Wolfram Programming Lab,
which is a good place for
learning the Wolfram Language.
Choosing Wolfram Programming Lab
opens a notebook
with some sample
Wolfram Language programs,
but to just get a new notebook,
you can click
the Create New Notebook button
or choose New Notebook
from the File menu
to get a new notebook
in the Wolfram Cloud |
Open Access system,
where you can enter content
and do calculations
much as you might do
in any other Wolfram Notebook.
After creating the notebook,
you can save the notebook
in the cloud,
which would of course require
logging into a cloud account,
or you can choose Download
from the File menu
to download the notebook
to a desktop system.
That's the end of the examples
for this section.
The basic features
of Wolfram Notebooks
work much the same
across all of these platforms,
but for features
that are different
on different platforms,
a good place to look
for more information
is the workflow guides
in the Wolfram documentation,
which gives separate
step-by-step instructions
for each platform.
For example, here is a page
of workflow guides
on working in notebooks,
and in this page
on creating a Text cell,
you can choose instructions
for the desktop platform
or for Wolfram Cloud
or for mobile devices
like tablets and smartphones.